Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Coua, who do you think is going to be found out?
It must be the one who victimized Lady Vertu.
It's a pity that Consort Fleur is still unaware.
"One may have more dreams over a long night."
Maybe His Majesty's anger will dissipate by the morning.
What do you think she'll do when she finds out what happened?
You know her.
She will either go to Great General Nian,
or kill Liu Ben immediately and then cry for His majesty's mercy.
True, if she finds out tonight she will create chaos, and infuriate His Majesty.
When we passed the Palace of Earthly Honor,
it was very quiet, wasn't it?
Yes, it was.
She is used to controlling the harem.
But now, My Lady ...
It is you who controls when she finds out ...
Go quickly then.
To the Palace of Earthly Honor?
Your Highness looked through the
medical books all day at the Imperial Infirmary.
And you haven't stop reading since you came back.
It's getting late now. Your Highness should take a break.
Your eyes are red and tired.
Why do you have so much time to talk?
Go get a few more candles.
Yes.
Your Majesty, terrible news... Liu Ben has been arrested.
What? Liu Ben was caught?
By whom? And where is he now?
I have no idea.
I just heard Attendant An's maid
talking to one of our maids about it.
Attendant An?
So it was Zhen Huan.
Could the assassins have been more useless?
Liu Ben is just a weak doctor.
Your Highness must stay calm.
Since Liu Ben has been arrested
he must confessed.
Instead of being angry, Your Highness
needs to calm down and think of a plan.
Go! Go tell my brother ...
Your Highness, the palace gates have already been locked.
If His Majesty is enraged,
even the Great General can't interfere with His Majesty's harem.
What should I do?
I can't just sit around here.
We are all in the same boat.
The two brothers from the Jiang family can't escape this.
-Zhou Ninghai.
-Yes.
Tell them to keep their mouths shut.
Go tell His Majesty in the early morning
that I am gravely ill.
I can only hope that will make His Majesty more lenient.
I understand. I will go right away.
It's necessary to keep the two doctors quiet.
But if Your Highness wants His Majesty to relent,
your long mutual affection is not enough.
Your Highness must give him what he wants the most now.
His Majesty will punish Your Highness
because Your Highness made a mistake.
A mistake deserves punishment, but a feat deserves reward.
If Your Highness can atone for the mistake by performing a great feat,
His Majesty will have a reason
to also prevent gossip about Your Highness.
I won't unfairly forgive a crime.
Go announce my decree to the Palace of Earthly Honor.
Yes, I'll do it now.
Every day I am consumed with worry about the plague at court.
I don't know if it will ever end.
"The strong work with their arms,
while the wise exert their minds."
Your Majesty is especially tired,
exhausting your arms and your mind.
Hearing you say that, I feel as if my bitter
work is as sweet as honey.
I didn't speak properly last night.
Don't take it to heart.
I dare not.
- Peace to Your Highness.
- Rise.
I need to see His Majesty.
His Majesty is about to leave for court.
I was just heading for the Palace of Earthly Honor.
That may be, but I have an urgent request for an audience.
Your Highness.
I'm afraid His Majesty is too busy to see you.
His Majesty can decide whether to see me or not.
Your job is to inform him.
Just a moment, Your Highness.
Your Majesty...
Concubine Fleur ...
Concubine Nian is here.
She requests an audience with Your Majesty.
What's the matter?
Concubine Nian came with Dr Jiang Cheng and Dr Jiang Shen.
She insists on seeing Your Majesty.
It seems to be something urgent.
Did you announce my decree?
Concubine Nian came in a rush,
and did not allow me to say anything.
If not, stop calling her "Concubine Nian".
Tell them to wait for me in the West Chamber.
Yes.
His Majesty is here.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty
Peace and grace to Consort Fleur.
- All rise.
- I thank Your Majesty.
What's so urgent?
I have great news for Your Majesty.
Drs. Jiang Cheng and Jiang Zhen have found a remedy for the plague.
I brought them here to report to Your Majesty.
Really?
Yes, but I am not well-versed in medicine.
I will let them explain to Your Majesty.
The six evil Qi, "wind, cold, summer-heat, damp, dryness, and fire",
invade through the nose and overrun the Upright Qi.
They attack the Upper Burner, Lung and Stomach,
and creates turmoil in the organs.
Don't be a pedant. Get to the point.
In most cases, the plague is caused by unsanitary food,
which damages the Spleen, Stomach, and Intestines.
We pored over the ancient medical books, and developed a prescription.
We call it the Plague Emergency Relief Formula.
It's warm nature dispels damp, and tonicifies Liver, Kidney, and innate qi.
Has it been examined by all the imperial doctors?
Is it effective?
It has.
Two eunuchs already took the formula,
and their fever broke after two doses.
Good.
Your Highness.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon.
Are you feeling unwell? Take a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
When Her Highness heard that the remedy
might be found in old medical books,
she stayed up all night going through the books.
Her Highness is also feeling weak because she
stayed up until early morning the last few days.
I know I am unworthy of serving Your Majesty
and always make Your Majesty angry.
But I would do anything to ease Your Majesty's burdens.
My beloved Consort has worked tirelessly.
- Su Peisheng.
- Your Majesty.
Take some servants and go with Dr Jiang.
Deliver the herbs immediately to Lady Vertu.
And then distribute it to everyone else infected.
Yes.
Lady Vertu?
I have restored Companion Shen's title
of which she was wrongfully deprived.
Shen must have suffered a lot.
She deserves compensation from Your Majesty.
Such happy news, Lady Sourire!
You and your sister don't need to worry anymore.
I thank Your Highness.
I dare not ask for Your Majesty's forgiveness
of my impetuous mistakes in the past.
I wish only that Your Majesty's good health
has not been harmed by the anger I have caused.
I am a humble commoner like "the roadside grass"
while Your Majesty's health is critical to everyone under Heaven.
All right.
You have made a great contribution to the country today.
If the medicine can cure the plague,
then everyone under Heaven will benefit.
My decision about awards and punishments will be fair.
I thank Your Majesty.
My Lady....
My Lady.
Do I still need to deliver His Majesty's
decree on Consort Fleur and the two doctors?
I know I should be asking His Majesty...
But since you were there, My Lady,
I humbly seek your guidance.
It seems to me that ...
you don't have to go, sir.
If you end up delivering a decree,
it will be one to promote her.
Dr. Wen, Dr. Jiang asked me to send you the medicine for Lady Vertu.
Has Dr. Jiang found a cure for plague as well?
I'll have a look.
His Majesty the Emperor!
- Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
You're having breakfast.
How's the food?
Whether it's insipid or delicious,
it's made by the Imperial Kitchen.
I dare not be picky.
Have a seat.
The Imperial Kitchen has to prepare food for everyone.
They can't make particular compromises for one person.
Likewise, I have to consider the greater good.
Yes, I understand.
The plague has been rampant.
Consort Fleur and Dr. Jiang exerted themselves pursuing the remedy.
Her hard work makes up for her mistake.
As for Liu Ben, I have granted him suicide.
This will, to an extent, compensate Lady Vertu.
Liu Ben is not the culprit behind this.
I understand.
But I need their assistance right now.
I have not forgotten what Lady Vertu suffered.
Nor will I let them off easy.
Your Majesty's health takes priority.
There's nothing else that concerns me.
That's good.
I also hope you can understand
that I won't be around as much.
I understand that Your Majesty will be busy with state affairs.
I have to go now.
His Majesty is leaving.
His Majesty has dark circles under his eyes.
He must have been working long hours.
His Majesty did work very late last night.
Ask my kitchen to make some ginseng soup
and send it to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
My Lady, you must understand that even
an emperor cannot do everything he wants.
In the harem, a woman's future and favor
all rest upon His Majesty's pillow.
But His Majesty's government also rests upon his pillow.
Love seems unconquerable but vanishes like smoke.
We both understand how it has to be.
That’s all too common in the palace.
My Lady, don't take it to heart.
I won't.
I'm just feeling disappointed.
I never thought His Majesty would cease to trust me.
I know His Majesty is a sensitive person.
When His Majesty wronged Meizhuang,
I wondered whether he would distrust me one day.
But now that it's happened, I'm surprised how much it saddens me.
Right and wrong are the least important among the concubines.
What matters is who His Majesty is willing to trust.
Instead of being sad, My Lady,
you have to start thinking about
how to reduce His Majesty's suspicion.
Why don’t you say "dispel His Majesty's suspicion"?
If you think you can do that, My Lady,
we can say that instead.
What happened?
What made you suddenly feel nauseous and heavy in your chest?
I thought you were in good prenatal health.
Your Majesty must not worry.
Lady Fuca simply ate too much.
It caused her chest to feel tight.
She just needs to have a lighter meal for dinner.
You could not tell the difference between being too full and being ill?
I was just scared, Your Majesty.
All right, you should lie down and have a good rest.
I still have some work to do. I’ll come back in the evening.
Your Majesty…
I know.
I said I will be here.
His Majesty is leaving.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Good.
This is great!
Nian Fu lived up to my expectation.
He quelled the rebellion at Mount Zhuozi.
Like father, like son.
Your Majesty, it’s almost time for lunch.
Would Your Majesty prefer to eat at the
Hall of Mental Cultivation or in the harem?
Didn’t the Imperial Kitchen make braised quail rice pearls today?
Yes, Your Majesty.
I remember it's Consort Fleur's favorite dish.
I will eat at the Palace of Earthly Honor.
What a coincidence!
The Palace of Earthly Honor has just
sent someone to invite Your Majesty over.
We seem to share one heart and one mind.
Braised abalone with pearl eggs,
stewed ham with fish maw,
chicken soup with shark skin,
and flowering cabbage with mushrooms.
These are all Your Majesty’s favorites.
These are the most time-consuming to make.
You must have gotten up before dawn to attend to the kitchen.
I must supervise the cooking of Your Majesty 's food.
I feel bad that you put
so much effort into just one meal for me.
It's my pleasure to spare no effort serving Your Majesty.
Your Majesty must be hungry after
half a day reviewing memorandums.
Your Majesty should start with some chicken soup to warm the Stomach.
Your Majesty seems to have a good appetite today.
Is there any good news?
Take a guess.
Is it because Nian Fu fulfilled Your Majesty's grace
by suppressing the rebels at Mount Zhuozi?
You have good sources.
You were informed very promptly.
The news of victory arrived early in the morning.
I am happy for Nian Fu as well.
Nian Fu did not fail his father's teachings and
has achieved success beyond his young age.
All morning I have been happy for Nian Fu's
first military victory.
How does Your Majesty intend to reward him?
Since you appreciate his hard work, I will reward him
silver and Four Treasures of the Study.
He is a man of the battlefields.
He wouldn't care for these.
So what do your suggest?
My brother's eldest son, Nian Bin,
has already been awarded a noble title.
Although Nian Fu is his second son,
he is as gallant as his brother.
What if Your Majesty also rewards him with a title?
So they will be of one heart in serving Your Majesty.
Nian Fu is very young, and this is his first military achievement.
It's too early to grant him a title.
He'll have to wait for a couple of years.
Your Majesty must care more about
my brother's opinion than mine.
If my brother had made this suggestion
Your Majesty would say he is acknowledging
the achievement of a warrior.
But if I make the same suggestion,
Your Majesty seems to think it's just a woman's short-sighted view.
Did your brother come to seek a reward for Nian Fu ?
My brother does adore Nian Fu the most.
But this is my own idea.
Let's eat.
All right.
I will reward your brother the first-order hereditary title
to be passed on to Nian Fu.
How's that?
Your Majesty.
You Majesty wouldn't agree until I got mad.
But I don't like being mad at you.
Your Majesty.
My Lady, here is the medicine.
My Lady, the medicine seems to be helpful.
The weather has been hot and cold.
It slows down my recovery.
"Recovering from sickness is like pulling silk from a cocoon."
It takes time.
As long as you nurse and nourish yourself,
My Lady, you will surely get well.
My Lady,
His Majesty wishes to see you in his
West Chamber at a quarter past one.
Thank you, sir.
Allow me to take my leave, My Lady.
Goodbye.
When was this memorandum from Nian Gengyao sent in?
About lunch time.
Consort Fleur has just sought a reward for Nian Fu at lunch.
And Nian Gengyao has sent in his request for rewarding
the worthy soldiers in the Mount Zhuozi Campaign.
They are "ploughing the same furrow."
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
You will lose your head if this is how you do your job!
Your Majesty, my offence deserves death.
I beg Your Highness would enlighten
my ignorant mind what I did wrong.
Your eyes are not sharp enough.
There are people inside the palace
trading information with the outside.
Yet you didn't know anything about it.
You have been as foolish as I have.
I entreat Your Majesty's forgiveness.
I beg Your Majesty would spare my life.
I will surely keep an eye out from now!
I will let you keep your head to atone for yourself.
Get up.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty ... Please have some tea and calm down.
Bring Lady Sourire here.
Yes.
Take a look at this.
I dare not interfere in state affairs.
This is a family matter. You have my permission.
Your Majesty, Zhao Zhiyuan impeached my father?
He accuses your father of
disrespecting
an honorable official and disobeying me.
His so-called disrespect ...
is referring to the fact that he
did
not kneel to General Nian like other officials.
Everyone believed that because I hold Nian Gengyao in high esteem,
they had to show utmost deference
to him as if it were obedience to me.
Your Majesty thinks highly of General Nian
for his contribution to the country.
But however significant his contribution is,
General Nian is but a servant
to the imperial family,
and officials like my father kneel
only to their emperors and lords.
Do you believe I think too highly of Nian Gengyao?
I dare not.
I only think that no matter how highly
Your Majesty values Nian Gengyao,
he wouldn't dare be arrogant enough to despise his peers.
Besides, Zhao Zhiyuan is the Review Director
of the Ministry of Public Works.
Why is he interfering on etiquette rather than tending to his own duties?
He always "sings the praises" of Nian Gengyao.
I will carefully consider the
implications of his memorandum.
Please be patient, My Lady.
His Majesty is talking with Lady Sourire.
Since His Majesty is busy,
I don't mind waiting for a bit longer.
Allow me to inform His Majesty one more time.
Thank you, sir.
Your Majesty.
What is it?
Attendant An has been waiting outside for an hour.
I'm busy right now.
Your Majesty, Lingrong is still recovering from her cough.
It's windy today and she shouldn't be waiting outside.
Will Your Majesty allow me to leave now?
But we haven’t finished the conversation.
- Su Peisheng.
- Yes.
Tell Attendant An that I can't spare any time to see her.
Tell her to go back and have a good rest.
Yes.
My Lady... I’m terribly sorry.
His Majesty requests you go back.
His Majesty is with Lady Sourire ... and not able to see you.
Sourire provides enough company for His Majesty.
I’ll go now.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady, you were standing in the cold wind for so long.
It made your cough worse.
I deserve it.
I already knew that Lady Sourire was inside.
But I insisted on waiting and making a fool of myself.
What was in Lady Sourire's mind?
She knows you are unwell.
She should have informed you earlier that His Majesty was busy.
But she would rather leave you outside waiting in the wind.
My Lady, you must be feeling cold.
Here's the hand warmer.
Your Highness, news came in that
Lady Sourire’s father has been demoted
to the lower fifth rank in the Censorate.
Yes, Your Highness.
Lady Sourire has been distinguished among the
new concubines because of her family background.
Now that her father is demoted, I wonder
if she will still hold her head high.
Zhao Zhiyuan is competent.
He took the hint from me and my brother
and staged the impeachment.
It appears that Lady Sourire now carries
little weight in His Majesty's heart.
Her freshness as a new concubine has expired.
That's true. She can't compare to Your Highness.
Your Highness has been favored by His Majesty all along.
I heard that His Majesty has only seen her once lately.
If she was a course in a meal, she
would have become stale and cold.
And it's up to Your Highness
when to take away the plate.
The soup is getting cold, My Lady.
You didn't eat any.
I feel upset. I have no appetite.
My Lady, you must be feeling upset about ... father.
But you have to care for your health.
What's the point of feeling upset?
It is His Majesty’s decree.
My Lady, your appetite has been low lately.
Shall I send for Dr Wen?
No.
Dr Wen is busy taking care of Meizhuang.
Perhaps I've eaten too much greasy food lately.
I feel tired. I'm going to bed now.
You've become a sleepy kitten, My Lady.
Although it is spring now, I still feel cold all over.
Go fill a hot water warmer for me.
His Majesty selected you for the night, My Lady.
You must look your best.
I went to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
I feel so sorry for Sourire.
I don't know how she could sleep.
Lady Sourire’s father was demoted.
She must be in distress,
worrying about everyone laughing at her.
So she found an excuse to avoid seeing people.
Sourire was always in high favor with His Majesty.
What a surprise!
You are still being kind to her, My Lady.
She kept you waiting outside the Hall of Mental Cultivation the other day.
Why do you feel sorry for her?
Coua, to tell you the truth,
Not only do I feel sorry, but also relieved.
Relieved?
She is better than me in every way.
She gained more favor from His Majesty
and has a better family background.
But now that her father is demoted
I no longer feel that our situations are so far apart.
She's no longer distantly above me.
My Lady, I’m sorry you felt that way.
I'm the one carrying an imperial heir.
Not Attendant An!
Why does His Majesty only see Attendant An?
Isn't she being a minx and taking advantage of my pregnancy?
Let her be, My Lady.
Lady Fuca always bullies the weak.
I haven't stopped hearing spiteful words since
moving into the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
This is nothing new.
Yes, My Lady.
Spring is coming and it's getting warmer.
Have you been feeling better?
I thank Your Majesty for asking.
I have been feeling much better.
Now that Consort Fleur assists
in the palace affairs
I have more time to myself.
You handed over the palace affairs to her
when your migraines became so severe.
Before I announced it, the concubines had
already started to report to Consort Fleur,
just as if they could "tell autumn from the falling leaves".
Consort Fleur is young ... and efficient.
Consort Fleur always assisted with the palace affairs.
She's experienced in the responsibilities.
The imperial harem is finally in harmony.
It would be inappropriate for me to keep
Consort Fleur out of palace management.
Consort Fleur made undeniable contributions to stop the plague.
And she is more prudent and decorous now.
It's about time to reinstate her authority in palace management.
I will follow Your Majesty's decision.
But there's something I wish to mention about Lady Sourire.
I know what you want to say.
I have punished Lady Sourire's father for his own mistake.
That does not affect Lady Sourire.
Your Majesty draws a clear line between the court and the harem,
but concubines don't always do so.
Your Majesty has always been very fond of Lady Sourire.
But now the concubines joke about her for what her father did.
If Your Majesty feels sympathetic for her,
please go visit her tonight.
But you told me that Attendant An missed me, didn't you?
I have already selected Attendant An for tonight.
Your Majesty has been
buried in state affairs.
How can any concubine not miss Your Majesty?
However, Attendant An has always been very close with Lady Sourire.
She will understand Your Majesty's sympathy for Lady Sourire.
That will be good. I don't want Lady Sourire
to feel upset because of her father.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Announce that Lady Sourire will
stay in the Hall of Mental Cultivation tonight.
Yes, Your Majesty.
My Lady, the Phoenix Carriage will be here soon.
Please be patient.
His Majesty rarely selects you for the night.
You must dress nicely ...
Otherwise His Majesty won't be interested in selecting you again.
Don't worry, Lady Fuca.
I will certainly convey to His Majesty that you miss him.
Are you laughing about me not being chosen to see His Majesty?
Why would I dare to? I just can't bear
seeing you distressed, missing His Majesty.
So I wish to speak to His Majesty for you.
How funny!
I'm carrying His Majesty's child.
I can see His Majesty whenever I want to.
You surely can.
But the next time you call for His Majesty,
better not say it's a "fetal disorder."
His Majesty will be annoyed if he hears that too much.
How dare you ...
Peace to Lady Fuca.
Peace to Attendant An.
What brings you here, Mr Su?
My lady, at His Majesty's behest,
you won't be serving him tonight.
But His Majesty selected me for tonight!
Yes, My Lady.
But His Majesty called for Lady Sourire just now.
The Phoenix Carriage has brought
Lady Sourire to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
It's not unusual that His Majesty changes his mind.
My Lady, perhaps His Majesty wishes you to have a good rest and recover from your cough sooner.
Thank you, Mr Su.
Allow me to take my leave.
It seems that I have overestimated Attendant An.
Now I don't even expect you will have a "next time."
What a shame.
You have dressed up so nicely
but His Majesty wouldn't even bother to look at you.
He selected you and regretted it.
However, you and Sourire are like sisters.
You two can take turns serving His Majesty.
It's no different.
But it's surprising that His Majesty would see her
when her father has just been demoted.
You've got a lot to learn from her, Lingrong.
Why ...
Why must she steal from me?
You've been losing weight
and have been more quiet with me.
Perhaps it's just springtime fatigue.
Try to be more active even if you feel tired.
We are more likely to get sick in the spring.
Your Majesty,
Lady Fuca feels uncomfortable due to fetal movement.
She wishes Your Majesty could keep her company.
Your Majesty should go.
I will be all right.
Ask the imperial doctors to take care of her.
Yes.
This is Lady Fuca's first time being pregnant.
Your Majesty should spend more time with her.
I appreciate your consideration.
You should stay here and go back tomorrow.
It's too cold to travel in the middle of the night.
Yes.
Peace and grace to Your Majesties.
You may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
You look unwell.
Sit down quickly.
You've got dark circles under your eyes
I heard that Lady Fuca invited Your Majesty last night.
Did she feel unwell?
She was fine.
Lady Fuca was petulant last night.
She was complaining that I arrived late and she was feeling nauseous.
That gave me a headache.
The plague has been under control in the palace
to which Consort Fleur made undeniable contributions.
Therefore I restore her authority to assist in palace management.
I thank Your Majesty.
You must fulfill the duties of a Consort and aid the Empress.
Congratulations, Fleur.
Concubine Estime has been serving me for over eight years.
For her dedication to the palace and gentle temperament,
she will be promoted to Consort.
Are you too happy to remember to say anything?
I ... humbly thank Your Majesty.
Your promotion ceremony will be held on the 19th of next month.
You entered the palace in the same year as Consort Fleur.
You are familiar with palace affairs.
You will aid Consort Fleur in lightening the burden on the Empress.
I will commit myself to assisting Her Majesty.
You may rise.
Congratulations, Consort Estime.
The scholars in Henan Province are
refusing to take the imperial examination.
So I will visit Henan tomorrow.
The Empress will be in charge of the palace affairs
with assistance from Consort Fleur and Consort Estime.
Don't worry, Your Majesty. I will do my utmost.
Madam.
I bow in respect before My Lady.
I heard His Majesty asked you to serve Meizhuang until her full recovery.
That must be hard work for you, Madam.
I do not deserve you saying that, My Lady.
Lady Vertu has been much better.
Meizhuang, how are you feeling to today?
I feel a bit better.
(We are so happy for Your Highness!)
Why are people talking loudly outside? What happened?
His Majesty promoted Concubine Estime to Consort.
Everyone is here to extend their congratulations.
It's also wonderful that you have been reinstated as Lady Vertu.
What difference does it make to me?
It's just a title.
You have been sick and suffered terribly during the confinement.
I understand that you feel upset.
If I say that that I meant it, will you believe me?
Since you feel better today, why don't we go out for a walk?
I don't want to go out.
It annoys me to see people.
I have peace and quiet in my chamber.
Nice seeing you here, Dr. Wen.
I haven't had a chance to thank you.
Meizhuang owes a lot to your excellent care.
I don't deserve the credit, My Lady.
It was the imperial doctors who found the remedy.
I only made small contributions.
Dr. Wen is being modest. Everyone in the
Imperial Infirmary knows you have excellent medical skills.
Why didn't anyone announce Dr. Wen's arrival?
It's so impolite of me with my hair disheveled and my face unwashed.
You're beautiful regardless.
When Xi Shi [an ancient beauty] was walking painfully and grimacing,
Dong Shi [an ugly woman] still wished to look like her and imitated her walk.
A beauty is a beauty whether she's sick or not.
Besides, Dr. Wen has been taking care of you
and knows you well.
We can forgo the formalities.
I appreciate your thoughtful and thorough care, Dr. Wen.
My Lady, you have been only eating porridge with pickles.
Although they are light and easy to digest,
they are not nourishing enough.
May I recommend some dietary therapies for you, My Lady?
I notice that Lady Sourire also looks a bit tired.
I recommend lamb stewed with ejiao [meat gelatin] from Dong’e.
It will enrich blood and qi.
Thank you for thinking of me.
You always inspire others to think of you.
Am I right, Dr. Wen?
It is my duty.
If you allow me, My Ladies,
I will go write the prescriptions now.
You must be tired from all the talking.
You should take a nap.
You don't look very well today. What's wrong?
Nothing. I didn't sleep well last night.
Although I've been "trapped in a well",
I can still see how the weather is changing outside.
Consort Fleur is now back to power again.
Consort Fleur regained her authority in palace management.
All our efforts are now in vain.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.